A Guide to the Carneal and Johnston Glass Negatives, c.1910s
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Carneal and Johnston Glass Negatives, c.1910s
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Carneal and Johnston
Ms2014-016
0.6 Cubic Feet 2 boxes [23 (8 x 10) glass dry plate negatives]
The collection consists of 23 glass dry plate negatives of architectural drawings made by the architectural firm Carneal and Johnston for various VPI campus buildings, including some that were never built, c.1910s.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Carneal and Johnston Glass Plate Negatives were purchased by University Relations and given to Special Collections in October 2014.
Biographical/Historical note
J. Ambler Johnston was born in 1885 and was a 1904 graduate of Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute. He also earned a master of science degree in 1905 from VPI. Johnston resided in Richmond, Virginia, where he served as a charter member of the Richmond Rotary Club and was a Civil War scholar. He died in 1974.
William Leigh Carneal, Jr., was born in Richmond on October 24, 1881, and graduated in 1903 from the Virginia Military Institute. He began his architectural practice around 1906 following a three year stint as a clerk in his father's company, Sitterding-Carneal-Davis Company. He died in 1958.
In 1908, Carneal and Johnston combined offices. The firm's first building was the original McBryde Hall on the VPI campus, completed in 1917. The firm helped to incorporate the Collegiate Gothic style to the campus landscape. For a brief period, the firm included a third partner and was known as Carneal, Johnston, & Wright. Both Carneal and Johnston retired in the 1950s. In 1999, the surviving firm of Carneal and Johnston merged with Ballou, Justice, & Upton Architects.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 23 glass dry plate negatives of architectural drawings made by the architectural firm Carneal and Johnston for various VPI campus buildings they designed, including the originial McBryde Hall and the original library/Gymnasium building, as well as proposed plans for an Alumni Hall (never built) and the Upper Quad Conversion (never built). Many of the plates are undated, but appear to come from the 1910s.
Arrangement
The 23 glass plate negatives are arranged in two boxes in the order that the plates were originally numbered.
Index Terms:
Genre and Form Terms
Architectural drawings
Subjects
University History
Corporate Names
Carneal and Johnston
Contents List
- No. 61, VPI General Plan (Master Plan), n.d. (Box 1)
- No. 64, VPI Main Tower, n.d. (Box 1)
- No. 65, VPI Prospective Main Group, n.d. (Box 1)
- No. 89, VPI Dormitory Section Side Elevation, n.d. (Box 1)
- No. 90, VPI Dormitory Section Exterior, n.d. (Box 1)
- No. 91, VPI Main Tower Exterior, n.d. (Box 1)
- No. 92, VPI Front Elevation Exterior, n.d. (Box 1)
- No. 93, VPI Gynasium Group Exterior, 1914 (Box 1)
- No. 94, VPI Prospective, n.d. (Box 1)
- No. 95, VPI General Plan, n.d. (Box 1)
- No. 96, VPI Prospective Exterior, n.d. (Box 1)
- No. 97, VPI Dormitory Section Exterior, n.d. (Box 2)
- No. 98, VPI Front Elevation Exterior, n.d. (Box 2)
- No. 107, Scale Drawings of VPI Shop Building Front and East Elevations, December 1913, 1913-1912 (Box 2)
- No. 113, VPI Gynasium Exterior, 1914 (Box 2)
- No. 114, VPI Dormitory Wing Exterior, n.d. (Box 2)
- No. 115, VPI General Plan, n.d. (Box 2)
- No. 116, VPI Main Tower Exterior, n.d. (Box 2)
- No. 117, VPI Front Elevation, n.d. (Box 2)
- No. 118, VPI Prospective Exterior, n.d. (Box 2)
- No. 155, VPI Dormitory Wing Exterior and Front Elevation Exterior, n.d. (Box 2)
- No. 181, Proposed VPI Alumni Hall Exterior, 1916-10-31 (Box 2)
- No. 182, Proposed VPI Alumni Hall First Floor Plan, 1916-10-31 (Box 2)